Mellonee V. Burnim Collection, 1861-1996, bulk 1976-1996 SC 7
Archives of African American Music and Culture
Mellonee V. Burnim Collection
1861-1996
1976-1996
Archives of African American Music and Culture
Burnim, Mellonee V. (Mellonee Victoria), 1950-
SC 7
145 Audiocassettes approximately 135 hours: analog, stereo
6 videotape reels EIAJ
9 Videocassettes VHS
8 Audiotape Reels 6 hours, 3 minutes
33 Slides
3 Items Binders of documentation. Collection also contains sheet music and song texts.
The collection includes Burnim's dissertation research on African American religious music conducted primarily in Indiana between 1976-1979 with an emphasis on gospel music performance and practice; and post-dissertation research on African and African American religious music conducted between 1980-1996 in the U.S., Cuba, Liberia, and Malawi. Also included is documentation of the 1984 Smithsonian American Folklife Festival and gospel sheet music. The collection was primarily recorded on analog audio formats and includes audiocassettes, open reel tapes, videocassettes, open reel video, slides, sheet music, song texts, and additional documentation.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series by topic and within subseries by creation date; series 4 arranged alphabetically by song title:
Series 1: African American Gospel/Religious Music
--- Subseries 1.1: Choir and Worship Service Recordings
--- Subseries 1.2: Interviews about Videotaped Gospel Performances
--- Subseries 1.3: Gospel Music Conventions
--- Subseries 1.4: Gospel and African American Music - Miscellaneous
Series 2: African and Cuban Religious Music
--- Subseries 2.1: African American Church Musical Exchange in Santiago de Cuba
--- Subseries 2.2: Monrovia, Liberia: Religious Music of Americo-Liberians
--- Subseries 2.3: Malawi
--- Subseries 2.4: Miscellaneous
--- Subseries 2.5: Slides
Series 3: Smithsonian Institution American Folklife Festival
Series 4: Gospel Sheet Music and Song Texts
Biographical / Historical
Mellonee V. Burnim received a Ph.D. in Folklore and Ethnomusicology from Indiana University in 1980; the title of her dissertation is "The Black Gospel Music Tradition: Symbol of Ethnicity." She joined the faculty of the IU African American Studies Department in 1980 and served as chair of the department from 1991-1994. She is currently a professor in the IU Department of Folklore and Ethnomusicology and the director of the Archives of African American Music and Culture at Indiana University. She has previously served as director of IU's Ethnomusicology Institute.
Burnim's primary areas of study include Black religious music and aesthetics, and music in the African Diaspora. She has led workshops in the history, performance, and instruction of African American religious music and has been a music consultant for various educational projects and documentaries. She has served as the Minister of Music for the Bethel African Methodist Episcopal (AME) and Fairview United Methodist churches in Bloomington. She also leads community choruses in the Bloomington area for special events.
Burnim's numerous publications and presentations have analyzed the aesthetics, cultural significance, and theological functions of gospel music. Her written works have become essential reading for those studying African American music. Her numerous articles can be found in journals and reference works including Ethnomusicology, The Western Journal of Black Studies, and The Garland Encyclopedia of World Music. Most recently, she and Portia Maultsby co-edited the second edition of their seminal work African American Music: An Introduction, which has been used as a key text on the subject in classrooms across the nation.
Access Restrictions
Use of time-based media materials (audio and video) may require production of listening or viewing copies.
Access to streaming audio, moving image, and full resolution digital image materials may currently be restricted to researchers who can authenticate with an IU account or who are physically present on campus. Remote streaming to individual researchers may be allowed with the completion of applicable forms.
For further information about access to online audiovisual materials, contact AAAMC staff at aaamc@indiana.edu.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift from Mellonee V. Burnim in 1998.
Scope and Contents
The Mellonee Burnim Collection consists primarily of analog field recordings of religious music in African American and African settings, most of which Burnim recorded between 1978 and 1996. The formats currently include 145 audiocassettes, 33 slides, 9 VHS videocassettes, 8 audiotape reels, 6 videotape reels, and 3 binders of documentation, as well as sheet music and song texts. These materials document over 150 hours of music and interviews recorded in the United States, Malawi, Liberia, and Cuba. Singers, composers, and gospel association leaders appear in recordings of worship services, funerals, choir rehearsals, gospel music workshops and festivals, and choral workshops. Burnim's interviews generally focus on the aesthetics and history of gospel music and its performance. The interviews include the perspectives of soloists, ministers, choral directors, congregants, and participants in gospel music workshops and the gospel music industry.
Series 1 includes Burnim's earliest recordings, which were made in conjunction with her dissertation research for "The Black Gospel Music Tradition: Symbol of Ethnicity" (Ph.D. dissertation, Indiana University, 1980). The formats in this series include 104 audiocassettes, 4 audiotape reels, and 6 videotape reels. Burnim recorded nearly all of her dissertation field recordings in 1978 and 1979, and these are also cataloged in her dissertation on pages 200--205. The purpose of Burnim's dissertation was "to define the extent and the mechanisms through which gospel music serves as a symbol of ethnicity among Black Americans in the United States" (Burnim 1980, page 2).
Burnim's primary research populations included the predominantly African American congregations of Mercy Mission Apostolic Church of Bloomington, Indiana, (217 North Elm Street) and Grace Apostolic Church of Indianapolis, Indiana (643 East 22nd Street). At the time of her research, these two churches differed according to the proximity of their location to urban centers, the structures and styles of church leadership, and the compositions of their congregation in terms of gender, race, and class. However, the two congregations shared denominational ties to Apostolic Pentacostalism. Burnim compared the "musical traditions" (Burnim 1980, page 8) of Mercy Mission and Grace Apostolic to those of other churches in Teague, Texas (Federation of Choirs, St. James U.M.E. Church) and Atlanta, Georgia (Wheat Street Baptist). Recordings of the choir rehearsals, worship services, broadcasts, and other performances are located in Subseries 1.1 along with Burnim's recorded reflections on these events. This subseries contains 33 audiocassettes, 4 audiotape reels, and 6 videotape reels.
The 12 audiocassettes in Subseries 1.2 include detailed commentaries on gospel music performances solicited by Burnim through the use of feedback interviews techniques. Interviewees were primarily culture-bearers, but also included two European American researchers studying White Pentacostalism. Data also was generated through transcription and analysis of recorded performances and Burnim's journal entries of her own experiences during participant-observation.
Subseries 1.3 includes 53 audiocassettes from additional short-term field research conducted at the August 1979 meeting of the Gospel Music Workshop of America (GMWA) and the Pentecostal Assemblies of the World, which were both held in New Orleans, Louisiana, as well as performances and participant interviews recorded by Burnim after the completion of her dissertation at various meetings of the GMWA and the National Convention of Gospel Choirs and Choruses (NCGCC) hosted throughout the United States in 1992-1995.
Burnim stated in a July 1997 interview with AAAMC staff that she recorded a cross-section of group activities occurring within each convention, including those involving no musical performance. Burnim feels this effort will support an accurate interpretation of the bodies, their meaning, and their significance to gospel music. Interviews probe the structure, history, and role of the GMWA and NCGCC conventions in African American gospel music. Such interviews include NCGCC President Kenneth Moales, GMWA Founding Member Ed Smith, NCGCC Historian Gladys Berryman, gospel pioneer Albertina Walker Brooks of the Caravans, and others. Burnim's recordings particularly document the participation of choirs and worshipers in the performance of gospel music at each convention--including instructional periods, rehearsals, and worship. Interviews with a Bahamanian choir director and a French singer document the international appeal of opportunities to learn more about gospel music in worship settings.
Subseries 1.4 contains 6 audiocassettes with miscellaneous content--primarily lectures and commercial recordings--related to African American gospel and religious music.
The post-dissertation field recordings from Liberia, Malawi, and Cuba in Series 2 reflect Burnim's ongoing interest in African American religious music in cross-cultural contexts. The 4 audiocassettes in Subseries 2.1 were recorded in Santiago de Cuba circa 1990 and document Burnim's participation with a touring group of African American ministers and professors of music. This group was sponsored by African American churches of the United States to present African American religious music to a Cuban audience in a context that educated listeners in the religious and historical context of the music. Burnim explained in her July 1997 interview with AAAMC staff that she values the recordings as examples of cross-cultural musical interaction, particularly the Cuban audience's reaction to the African American musical styles. Ethnomusicologist and AAAMC founder, Dr. Portia K. Maultsby, participated as an organist for the group.
Subseries 2.2 consists of 4 audiocassettes from Burnim's 1989 trip to Monrovia, Liberia. In the 1997 interview, Burnim explained that this research was intended to serve as a preliminary study for a longer ethnomusicological project examining the religious music of Americo-Liberians. The outbreak of civil war in Liberia after the conclusion of her visit there led Burnim to postpone indefinitely plans for further research in the area. According to Burnim, the recordings of worship and choir rehearsals of the interdenominational Tuesday Cottage Prayer Band and St. Peter's Lutheran Church confirm the presence of African American sacred songs in these West African congregations. Burnim's selection of research sites drew upon contacts made by ethnomusicologist Ruth M. Stone (Professor and Chair, Folklore Institute, Indiana University) during her long-term field research in Liberia. Burnim explained in the 1997 interview that her own Liberian field research directly offers data for comparison with ethnomusicological studies focused on indigenous Liberian music, such as Dr. Stone's study of Kpelle epic.
The 33 audiocassettes and 6 videocassettes in Subseries 2.3 were recorded during Burnim's residence in Zomba, Malawi--where she was visiting associate professor at Chancellor College of the University of Malawi (1991)--and her brief return as a director for the university's annual Choral Workshop in 1992. While there, Burnim conducted field research on music in several Malawian Christian communities. As in Liberia, Burnim investigated the use of African American religious music in Malawian contexts, primarily in the cities of Blantyre and Zomba. In addition to worship services in churches, Burnim recorded the Mhango Salvation Singers' gospel-styled performance at an outdoor festival and received a copy of a commercially-produced studio recording from the group. As with this tape, the commercially-produced recordings of the Burnim Collection generally offer supplemental information on the repertoire or broader musical scene of musicians Burnim recorded during field research.
Though English language predominates in the Choral Workshop recordings, most of the Malawian field recordings include music and speech in indigenous Malawian languages, particularly Chichewa. Therefore, Burnim obtained help from a few of her Malawian students, who served as field research assistants and translators. Several of the field recordings from Malawi contain sections where communications in an indigenous language are translated or summarized in English. Burnim noted in the July 1997 interview, however, that her limited familiarity with indigenous Malawian traditions necessitated additional clarification by Malawians. To assist in receiving Malawian interpretations of such field recordings, Burnim conducted feedback interviews with members of a church congregation. For these feedback interviews, she played a videotaped worship service and recorded the church members' responses (in their indigenous language) to the events of their service. The Burnim Collection contains both the videotaped performances used for the feedback interview and the audiotaped responses of the congregants.
In addition to performances featuring religious music in Malawi, Burnim recorded a concert featuring the Vaal Reef Choir of South African miners and interviewed one member of the all-male group. This performance presented--in the order printed here--repertoire from Western European art music, arranged choral (African American) spirituals, popular music in English, and indigenous South African music. According to Burnim's 1997 interview with AAAMC staff, this performance invited the examination of social issues. Burnim said that differences along the lines of gender, race, and ethnicity between the White South African director and the Black South African members of the Vaal Reef Choir are implicated in the musical performance and organizational operations of the group. At the time of the field recordings, South Africa's system of apartheid strictly enforced White supremist rule over the Black majority population.
Subseries 2.3 contains 2 audiotape reels and two videocassettes with miscellaneous content and Subseries 2.4 contains of 33 slides related to Burnim's Africa research.
Series 3 consists of 4 videocassettes of Black music performances hosted on the Philadelphia Stage at the Smithsonian Institution American Folklife Festival from July 1-17, 1984, while Series 4 contains 39 pieces of gospel sheet music and song texts dating from approximately 1861-1981.
gospel music; African American Church Musicians; Spirituals (Songs); Gospel musicians; African Americans--Music; African Americans--Religion; Gospel music--Liberia; Americo-Liberians--Music; Americo-Liberians--Religion; Liberia--Music; Liberia--Religion; Gospel music--Malawi; Malawi--Music; Malawi--Religion; Gospel music--Cuba; Cuba--Music; Cuba--Religion; Gospel Music Workshop of America; Pentecostal Assemblies of the World; Grace Apostolic Church (Indianapolis, Ind.); National Convention of Gospel Choirs and Choruses, Inc.; Festival of American Folklife
- 1. African American Gospel/Religious Music, 1976-1996; 104 Audiocassettes + 4 audiotape reels (3 hours, 54 minutes), 6 videotape reels; (approximately 98 hours)
  - 1.1. Choir and Worship Service Recordings, 1976-1996; 33 Audiocassettes + 4 audiotape reels (3 hours, 54 minutes) and 6 videotape reels; (approximately 37 hours)
    - Mercy Mission Apostolic Church, Bloomington, Indiana. Burnim's Reflections on Initial Visit, 1976 March 7; C001; cass 1780; 1 Audiocassette 18 minutes
      Reference Copies
      Preservation master file(s): 24 bit/96 kHz Broadcast Wave File (BWF)
      Production master file(s): 16 bit/24 kHz Broadcast Wave
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 341
    - Mercy Mission Apostolic Church, Bloomington, Indiana. Choir Rehearsal and Radio Broadcast, 1976 March 14; C002; cass 1781; 1 Audiocassette 52 minutes
    - Mercy Mission Apostolic Church, Bloomington, Indiana. Choral Ensemble Rehearsal and Radio Broadcast, 1976 March 21; C003; cass 1782; 1 Audiocassette 93 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 342--CDREF 343
    - Grace Apostolic Church, Indianapolis, Indiana. Sunday Morning Radio Broadcast on WTLC FM 105, 1978 October 9; C1; cass 1783; 1 Audiocassette 62 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 344
    - Grace Apostolic Church, Indianapolis, Indiana. Bishop's Choir and Choral Ensemble, approximately 1978; C2; cass 1784; 1 Audiocassette 51 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 345
    - Apostolic Light Performance, Whittenberger Auditorium, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana, 1978 November 6; C3; cass 1785; 1 Audiocassette 63 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 346
    - Black College Gospel Choir Workshop, Marriott Hotel, Atlanta, Georgia, 1978 November 24; C4; cass 1786; 1 Audiocassette 45 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 347
    - Wheat St. Baptist Church, Atlanta, Georgia. Morning Worship Service, approximately 1978 November 26; C5; cass 1787; 1 Audiocassette
      Currently unavailable - Contact AAAMC staff for details
      General
      Unable to transfer due to technical problems with original cassette.
    - Grace Apostolic Church, Indianapolis, Indiana. Sunday Morning Worship Service, 1979 March 25; C7; cass 1789; 1 Audiocassette 46 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 351--CDREF 352
      Although labeled and dated differently, cass 1789, side A seems to be a duplicate of cass 1788.
    - Grace Apostolic Church, Indianapolis, Indiana. Easter Morning Worship Service, 1979 April 15; C6; cass 1788; 1 Audiocassette 80 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 350
      Although labeled and dated differently, cass 1788 seems to be a duplicate of cass 1789, side A.
    - Grace Apostolic Church, Indianapolis, Indiana. Morning Worship Service, 1979 May 13; C8; cass 1790; 1 Audiocassette
    - First Christian Missionary Baptist Church, Indianapolis, Indiana. The Bishop's Choir Concert, 1979 May 18; R101--R102; OR 35--OR 36; 2 Audiotape Reels 119 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 332--CDREF 334
    - Grace Apostolic Church, Indianapolis, Indiana. The Bishop's Choir Rehearsal, 1979 May 22; R103; C9; OR 37; cass 1791; 1 Audiotape Reel + 1 audiocassette (93 minutes); (64 minutes)
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 335; CDREF 355--CDREF 356
      Side B listed as a continuation of OR 37; cassette itself is dated as 5/15/1979.
    - Grace Apostolic Church, Indianapolis, Indiana. Second Gospel Music Festival, 1979 June 2; C11; RV-1; cass 1792; 1 Audiocassette + 1 videotape reel; (92 minutes)
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 357--CDREF 358
      Reference copy of videotape reel currently unavailable - Contact AAAMC staff for details
      See pages 208--211 of Burnim's dissertation for concert program. Videotape reel was transferred as part of the EVIA Digital Archive Project but is currently unavailable to the public. See http://www.eviada.org/ for details.
    - Grace Apostolic Church, Indianapolis, Indiana. Morning Worship Service, 1979 June 3; C12--C13; cass 1793--cass 1794; 2 Audiocassettes 110 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 359--CDREF 360
      Unable to transfer cass 1794 due to technical problems with original cassette.
    - Grace Apostolic Church, Indianapolis, Indiana. The Bishop's Choir Rehearsal, 1979 June 5; R104--R105; OR 38--OR 39; 2 Audiotape Reels 101 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 336--CDREF 337
    - Grace Apostolic Church, Indianapolis, Indiana. The Bishop's Choir Rehearsal, 1979 June 12; R106; OR 40; 1 Audiotape Reel 69 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 338
    - St. James U.M.E. Church, Teague, Texas. Gospel Music Festival, 1979 June 22; RV-2--RV-3; 2 videotape reels
      See pages 212--214 of Burnim's dissertation for concert program. Videotape reels were transferred as part of the EVIA Digital Archive Project but is currently unavailable to the public. See http://www.eviada.org/ for details.
    - Grace Apostolic Church, Indianapolis, Indiana. The Bishop's Choir Rehearsal, 1979 June 25; C15--C16; cass 1795--cass 1796; 2 Audiocassettes 124 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 361--CDREF 362
    - Grace Apostolic Church, Indianapolis, Indiana. The Bishop's Choir, 7th Anniversary Concert, 1979 June 30; C17--C18; RV-4; cass 1797--cass 1798; 2 Audiocassettes + 1 videotape reel; (121 minutes)
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 363--CDREF 365
      See pages 215--216 of Burnim's dissertation for concert program. Videotape reel was transferred as part of the EVIA Digital Archive Project but is currently unavailable to the public. See http://www.eviada.org/ for details.
    - Zion Pentecostal Church, Indianapolis, Indiana. Mass Choir, 1979 July 22; C19; cass 1799; 1 Audiocassette 20 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 365
    - Grace Apostolic Church, Indianapolis, Indiana. Pentecostal Ambassadors Annual Concert; Burnim's Field Notes Regarding the Pentecostal Ambassadors' Concert, 1979 August 5; C20; cass 1800; 1 Audiocassette 91 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 366--CDREF 367
    - Interview with Sister Margaret Bryant Recorded at Bryant's Home; Burnim's Reflections on Grace Tent Meeting and Pentecostal Ambassadors' Anniversary Concert, Indianapolis, Indiana, approximately 1979 August 4--5; C200; cass 1806; 1 Audiocassette 33 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 375
    - Second Christian Church, Indianapolis Indiana. Sarah Jordan Powell in Concert; Comments by Maragret Bryant; Burnim's Reflections on Concert and Bryant's Comments, 1979 October 14; C25; cass 1805; 1 Audiocassette 82 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 373--CDREF 374
    - Grace Apostolic Church, Indianapolis, Indiana. The Bishop's Choir, 8th Anniversary Concert, 1980 June 29; 1-1; cass 1819; 1 Audiocassette 82 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 393--CDREF 394
    - Martin Luther King Workshop Choir, Donald Vails, conductor, Boston University, School of Theology, Boston, Massachusetts, Program, 1981 November 14; 2-1--2-2; cass 1820--cass 1821; 2 Audiocassettes 127 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 395--CDREF 396
    - Freestone Travelers [Gospel Quartet] 7th Anniversary Concert, Furney Richardson Community Center, Texas, 1982 May; RV-5--RV-6; 2 videotape reels
      Videotape reels were transferred as part of the EVIA Digital Archive Project but are currently unavailable to the public. See http://www.eviada.org/ for details.
    - Memorial Service for Edward Smith, New Bethel Baptist Church, Detroit, Michigan, 1994 April 5; 15-1--15-3; cass 1918--cass 1920; 3 Audiocassettes 236 minutes
      Access file(s): 16 bit/24 kHz Broadcast Wave
      Content
      cass 1918. Albertina Walker
      cass 1919. Sarah Jordan Powell; Vanessa Bell Armstrong
      cass 1920. John P. Kee; Vanessa Bell Armstrong
    - Mattie Moss Clark Funeral, Bailey Temple Church of God in Christ, Detroit, Michigan., 1994 September 28; 15-4--15-5; cass 1921--cass 1922; 2 Audiocassettes 198 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 644--CDREF 647
    - Light of the World Church, Indianapolis, Indiana. Service "Secret Place", 1996 November 18; 22-1--22-2; cass 1907--cass 1908; 2 Audiocassettes 188 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 632--CDREF 635
  - 1.2. Interviews about Videotaped Gospel Performances, 1979-1980; 12 Audiocassettes 11 hours, 55 minutes
    - Black Culture Center, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana. Group feedback Interview with Lois Davenport, Norman Thompson, and Jackie Foster, 1979 October 17; C301; cass 1809; 1 Audiocassette 62 minutes
      Compact disc(s): CDREF 377--CDREF 378
      Topics: Gospel vs. R&B, sacred vs. secular; Pentecostal restrictions on dress, popular music.
      Side B (CDREF 378) contains a recording of an unidentified speaker/conference, date and location unknown, although possibly Terre Haute, Indiana.